RAJNIKANT YADAV

 Lucknow Uttar Pradesh, Indiahttps://github.com/rajnikant-yadav

EDUCATION

B.Tech in Electronics and Communication Engineering CGPA: 8.3/10.0

2017-2021

EXPERIENCE

Software Product Developer - I **XLSCOUT**

July 2021 - Present

Mohali

- Automated patent searching and analysis webpage with identity and access management, generating well-formatted reports using webpage data. Created and managed databases (Postgres, MongoDB, Elasticsearch, Google Cloud Storage), handled Keycloak integration.
- I design, implement, maintain, debug, and refactor microservices for patent searching and analysis.
- Conducted automated unit testing and developed interactive API documentation for the Backend application.

Research Analyst Trainee

TT Consultants

Feb 2021 - Jun 2021

Mohali

 As a Research Analyst Trainee at TT Consultants, I conducted Novelty, Invalidation, and Infringement searches.

PYTHON DEVELOPMENT INTERN

Conscript HR Advisors Pvt Ltd

May 2020 - Jul 2020

• I wrote Python scripts for data scraping and preprocessing, while also contributing to the development of a Job Aggregator.

MACHINE LEARNING INTERN

Olcademy

🛗 Sept 2019 - Dec 2019

♀ Work from home

 Contributed to the development of an Olcademy discussion forum, a Pearson Tests of English Simulator, and engaged in web scraping and data preprocessing tasks

PROJECTS

Web Automation

- Automated website interactions using Puppeteer, Express.js, Axios, and Node.js.
 Deployed on AWS EC2 via Docker containers. API documented with Swagger for clarity and scalability.
- TOOL NodeJs, AWS, Docker, ExpressJs, Puppeteer, Javascript, Swagger

Ecommerce Website

₩ Nov 2022

- Created an E-commerce site with Node.js, React.js, MongoDB. Features secure
 user authentication, product management, and AWS hosting for optimal performance.
- TOOL- NodeJs, ReactJs, Mongodb, AWS, JWT, ExpressJs, Axios, Javascript

Report Generator API

Aug 2021

- Server-side report generator API that produces well-formatted, visually appealing PDFs, XLSX, Word, and PPT documents. Utilizes web automation with Puppeteer or retrieves data from APIs to generate reports and delivers them directly to users via email.
- TOOL Puppeteer, NodeJs, Fastify, MongoDB, PDFKit, Pdfmake, Nodemailer

ABOUT

A software product developer specializing in modern JavaScript, with hands-on experience in software design and application development, and hands-on experience with cloud infrastructure like AWS and GCP. A quick learner with solid time management and multitasking skills, possessing exceptional troubleshooting and problem-solving abilities, empowered to adapt to diverse situations and contribute to personal and collective growth.

TECHNICAL SKILLS



Programming Languages

JavaScript Python C, C++



Libraries/Frameworks

Puppeteer	Pdfmake Docker
Keycloak Fastify Nodejs	
PdfKit S3 google-cloud/storage	
Express	

Tools and Databases

MongoDB MySQL Elasticsearch

CERTIFICATIONS

AWS Architect Associate Logiclabs Technologies

Mov 2022 - No Expiration Date

Machine Learning

Coursera

🛗 Aug 2019 - No Expiration Date

PERSONAL SKILLS

Self Starter Flexible&Adaptable

Leadership Communication

EXTRA-CURRICULAR

Crew Member

IEEE

m Sep 2018 - Apr 2019

Technical Head

Technovatorz

Cct 2019 - Present

JUIT: Sports Club member